hello and welcome back to my Channel
today I want to talk about something
called toxic
femininity in order to talk about toxic
femininity we must first talk about
toxic
masculinity I think most people are
familiar with toxic masculinity or at
least have some idea of what it's about
but it's not so common to hear people
talk about toxic femininity which is the
topic of today's
video both toxic masculinity and toxic
femininity negatively impacts men and
women but toxic femininity is harder to
detect because it's much more subtle
than toxic
masculinity toxic masculinity is the
idea that our society pressures men and
boys to conform to what are considered
traditional masculine traits to their
own
detriment according to toxic masculinity
men are socially conditioned to portray
certain masculine characteristics which
causes them to be prone to things like
aggression emotionlessness being power
hungry being dominant sexually entitled
headstrong and
violent the idea is that these traits
emerge in men who have been socialized
to be a stereotypical heterosexual male
and this interferes with their ability
to develop their emotions and display
vulnerability and healthy
relationships according to the doctrine
of toxic masculinity men who have been
conditioned to be ultr masculine are
also a threat to women because it leads
to domestic violence and crime in
general the vast majority of violent
criminals are male including offenders
of domestic abuse and sexual assault and
this is attributed to the socialization
that toxic masculinity brings about the
belief is that toxic masculinity is
oppressive for men because it causes
them to stifle their emotions and it
harms women by encouraging men to
dominate
them in an article I read from
verywellmind.com concerning toxic
masculinity members of the American
Psychological Association have concluded
that drawing on more than 40 Years of
research the APA suggests that features
of traditional masculinity are
psychologically
harmful they also report that
socializing boys to suppress their
emotions creates damage both inwardly
and outward ly I reject the assertion
that boys who grow up to embrace
traditional masculinity are
automatically bad people who are
destined to become emotionally repressed
and abusive
men so now I'm going to talk about
standards I genuinely feel bad for men
in our postmodern Society because the
standards that women have for men have
become
unreachable women typically want men who
are protective courageous
self-sufficient ambitious and
independent but only in the right ways
they want a man who is capable of being
a provider but only if he communicates
Like a Woman They want to pick and
choose which masculine traits they want
in a man but they don't seem to
understand that this is not a buffet
right this is not
Ponderosa you can't pick and choose
which masculine traits are acceptable
because all of the traits associated
with toxic masculinity are interrelated
and come from the fact that men if D to
hunt you could say that male aggression
is always bad except that it's not if
someone breaks into your home and
attempts to assault you would you as a
woman want your man to get aggressive
with that person as a means to protect
you and your children what about war men
evolve to hunt and protect women and
children and that's why they get angry
and aggressive because it served a vital
purpose in the past women are trying to
reverse entire eras evolution by
dictating which emotions men are allowed
to feel and it can't be done having the
ability to put emotions aside when
making serious decisions makes someone
competent emotionality causes people to
make bad decisions and do irrational
things anger is one of the most natural
things there is it comes from the
amydala which is one of the oldest parts
of our brains in the past anger
motivated men to fend off predators and
combat hostile humans what's happening
now is that anger must be suppressed by
men in order to conform to society's
standards however anger doesn't just
disappear it comes out in other ways
like road rage for instance in
postmodern America we now have mass
Shooters in this country which is a
manifestation of unresolved anger
dwelling underneath the surface of men
that finally
explodes they've been told by women
their entire life that it's not
acceptable to get mad I know I'm not a
man and I don't have a son but there's
way too much man bashing that's going on
in society and it has to stop because
men are people it's not
right so now that we've talked about
toxic masculinity what is toxic
femininity toxic femininity manifests
itself in different ways and like I said
earlier can be a lot harder to detect
because it's way more subtle it's way
more underhanded and devious just like
how toxic masculinity embodies several
different characteristics of traditional
masculinity toxic femininity does the
same thing but with feminine
characteristics however there seems to
be a disagreement on what exactly toxic
femininity
is many sources on the internet Define
toxic femininity as the forced adherence
of women
to behave in ways that are
conventionally feminine this restricts
women to Binary gender roles and limits
their freedom in order for them to be
more appealing to men these feminine
qualities include passiveness
selflessness compliance sensitivity
politeness and
compassion according to an article from
Healthline environments like school work
online and social media contribute to
toxic femininity whenever they normalize
aspects of conventional gender roles
such as suggesting that women should
shave their legs or have
children according to author SEMA Anand
who writes about topics relating to
intimacy between men and women there are
stereotypical attributes of women that
are enforced by society and that cause
women to conform to feminine stereotypes
which hold women back from success and
the achievement of their goals the
presence of this form of toxic
femininity Coes women to be quiet loving
submissive pretty and
Cooperative it also leads women to defer
to the superior guidance of men which
impedes women's happiness and Freedom by
causing them to take a more submissive
role in their relationships with men and
this is somehow suffocating for women
because being a housewife and a
stay-at-home mom is some kind of
hellscape where they end up turning into
Stepford Wives even if this were true
what is so toxic about being a
traditional wife where are all the
victims of cooperation and
politeness I have a problem with this
definition of toxic femininity because I
really don't think girls and women are
being coerced into being wives and
mothers in fact I think it's the
opposite feminism encourages women to
behave like men in every way girls are
trained from a young age that their
future happiness depends on them
establishing a good career before
starting a family they learn how to
compete with men instead of how to
collaborate with
men in our society men have higher
status than women this means that there
is status associated with masculinity
but not with
femininity women rushed into the
workforce and began doing the same jobs
as men but men did not enter into
feminine jobs and roles feminists have
pushed us to act more like men in order
to raise our status but when a man acts
like a woman he's lowering his status
the classic example of this which isn't
as relevant today as it was in the past
is that the Tomboy who plays softball
and likes GI Jo's gets a pat on the back
but the boy who plays with Barbies is
seen as a in my opinion feminism
should be called manism because it
doesn't support the mature sacred
feminine at all in fact it opposes
it in our postmodern world classically
feminine traits are seen as bad because
of feminism the ability to be submissive
vulnerable and nurturing as a wife and
mother are not forms of abuse nor do
they rob women of their happiness they
are strengths they're deserving of
respect when you talk about women you're
talking about billions of people there
are variations to everything there are
bell curves for everything and it's
nearly impossible for four billion
people to all have the same
preferences but I do think that a
traditional lifestyle where the woman is
focused on her family over her career
would be a good thing for the majority
of women the problem is that in our
society we've been indoctrinated by
feminism to believe that femininity is
weak and bad and that masculinity is
powerful and good
being quiet loving submissive and pretty
are good things they create a polarity
between men and women in relationships
that emphasizes the existing sexual
dimorphism and creates more solidarity
within male and female heterosexual
relationships when a woman is being
traditionally feminine she's also being
kind compassionate and nurturing which
are all admirable traits these
characteristics a Aid her in raising her
children and establishing healthy bonds
with other people if you're a woman
there is nothing wrong with embracing
the Divine mature feminine inside of
you the other more accurate definitions
of toxic femininity are based on the
idea that there are feminine traits used
by women to harm other people women have
the ability to use their sexuality as a
weapon in order to control the men in
their lives
additionally they can be catty conniving
and insincere to the point of
viciousness especially when they're
attempting to bully another woman a
woman's level of duplicity will allow
her to be kind and supportive to
someone's face while simultaneously
sabotaging them behind their
back in the past being able to
manipulate the behavior of others by
being cunning and beguiling must have
been advantageous because men are twice
as strong as women but in today's
society the misuse of these feminine
characteristics can easily result in the
unnecessary suffering of other
people one of the most well-known forms
of toxic femininity is the classic fem
fetal archetype which is representative
of a woman who uses her beauty and
sexuality to commit crimes and take
advantage of men through seduction and
treachery the fetal archetype has been
largely exonerated by postmodern
feminism which has rebranded it as a
woman who courageously defies boundaries
and takes control over her life and
sexuality Sharon Stone played a fatal
character in the movie Basic Instinct
another example from Greek mythology are
the siren who tempted odys and his men
to swim out to meet their deaths at Sea
by using their enchanting
voices women have a complex relationship
with power most often they feel
powerless in any given situation and
that's because fundamentally they are
women are at a physiological
disadvantage when compared with men the
average man is stronger than 97% of
women through social and psychological
Evolution women adapted to this
asymmetry by using covert methods of
manipulation women commonly resort to
passive aggressive behavior to gain
status and to get closer to power in the
past the only real source of power that
women had over men was their sexuality
but we have since given that
away a large part of what makes
something valuable is scarcity when
something is limited and in high demand
then it's also considered to be highly
valuable an example of this is the case
of diamonds so diamonds are not rare in
nature there's a company called De Beers
who owns all of the diamond mines they
have a monop
in the continent of Africa and they
limit the number of diamonds that go to
the market for Jewelers to purchase
unlike gold which is actually scarce
diamonds are very common essentially
they're just carbon and carbon is
abundant on Earth deers has created an
artificial scarcity as part of their
marketing campaign and it works because
even though diamonds aren't rare in
nature it's still difficult to obtain
them and this is part of what makes them
so
valuable there is a book by a woman
named Louise Perry called the case
against the sexual Revolution which was
published in
2022 in the book it talks about the
changes in social norms that took place
as a result of the 1960s second wave
feminism
movement according to this book in the
past sexual access for men was more
valuable than it is today because women
kept it scary by not losing their
virginity until they were married even
though there were definitely people who
did have sex before marriage by in large
it was a sexual Norm that girls didn't
deviate from if men were interested in
promiscuous and casual sex then they
would have to go through prostitutes to
get it men had to make themselves
suitable for marriage if they wanted an
intimate relationship with a woman but
when the sexual Revolution took place
women's stopped guarding their virginity
the birth control pill gave women the
ability to control their fertility and
legalized abortions made Parenthood
optional during the sexual Revolution
the ideology of feminism prevailed which
told women and girls that in order to be
equal women needed to start having sex
like men treating it like any other
social interaction since that time
sexual expectations have changed under
the pretense that there are no longer
consequences of having sex even though
in reality that's not
true in today's society a lot of young
girls and women think their virginity is
a burden that they must get rid of
because they want to fit in with their
peers the problem is that sex is now
cheap and easy to get and the group that
suffers from this state of affairs is
women the value of sex has decreased to
the point where it's basically worthless
and with that women have lost their only
real power in the world powerless women
take out their aggression on other women
because it makes them feel like they're
in control if women began to gatekeep
their sexuality like they did in the
past they would regain a lot of power
and they wouldn't feel the need to take
out their resentment on other women in
order to feel better there's a surge of
pleasure to be gained by having the
ability to convince a group of people to
ostracize another
woman when women abuse other women their
actions can be unbelievably
cruel women often bully other women
especially at the workplace social
exclusion is one of the most common
tactics employed by female bullies who
want to Rob Other Women of status move
them further away from power and destroy
their reputations through gossip
backbiting and spreading rumors they
will intentionally leave the targeted
woman out of group activities and rally
other members of the group to
essentially shun them women become
monsters when they do this to each
other when boys attack other boys
through physical aggression at school
there are always
consequences usually one or both boys is
punished through suspension or
expulsion fighting is not tolerated in
public schools at all however there are
no punishments when girls bully other
girls through covert tactics the answer
is always more mental health care for
the girls who are bullied and no
punishment for the bullies themselves in
2023 the CDC reported that the rate of
suicidal ideation in teen girls has
risen to 30% from 24% in
2019 this rise in girls having suicidal
thoughts and feelings is attributed to
the rise of online bullying that takes
place on social media platforms like
Instagram
why do women bully other women often
times it's because of
jealousy why are women so threatened by
each other the answer lies in the
expectations for women when they go out
with men if you're a female and you go
on a first date with a high status guy
the expectation is that you will sleep
with him on the first date if you choose
not to there are so many other women who
will and he's likely to not go out with
you again because he can find what he's
looking for with relative ease from
someone
else however if you do sleep with him on
the first date your value as a woman
will be reduced you will depreciate in
value as you experience the shame that
comes with casual onetime sexual
encounters so it's damned if you do
damned if you
don't some people include shaming
as a form of lateral abuse and toxic
femininity that must addressed and dealt
with shaming is when women accuse
Other Women of being too sexual it can
take the form of belittling a woman for
wearing revealing clothing or slandering
women behind their backs by engaging in
overly sexual behavior due to the
influence of modern woke and feminist
ideologies in Western society which
promote sex positivity for both sexes
women are now highly discouraged from
shaming other women
it's become unacceptable in our society
which is obsessed with
tolerance I read a book about narcissism
one time that said the origins of
narcissism in people is rooted in
shame the problem that narcissistic
people have is that they can't under any
circumstances tolerate the feeling of
shame but the problem is that a certain
amount of healthy shame is good for
people and enforcing that shame can be
productive the goal of people who
shame is to humiliate women who are
promiscuous and this serves a purpose in
society these women are lacking in
humility and there's a sense of shame
that occurs organically in women who
have one night stands in college dorms
it's called the the walk of shame that
happens when a woman leaves the dorm
room of a guy she just slept with the
next morning and everybody knows what
happened the night before healthy shame
helps people to respect boundaries and
rules if women were more reluctant to
sleep with men they just met then the
expectations of a first date would
change women sabotage themselves when
they behave this way shame keeps people
aligned and helps them to maintain
relationships due to female hypergamy
women are selective about who they want
to sleep with this comes from Evolution
and from women wanting the best DNA for
their offspring
it's a totally natural thing but it
becomes toxic when all women are
competing against each other for the top
10% of men and these men who are in the
upper echelon of valuable men in reality
are not going to be the best fathers for
their offspring I think the phenomenon
of passport Bros is interesting passport
Bros are men who go to other less
developed countries to find a wife they
do this because women in other countries
aren't nearly as judgmental about men
and are more likely to be happy with a
man the way he is unlike American women
and their impossible
criteria this is an example of how a
feminine trait like hypergamy in the
right context can be toxic it results in
women never finding a husband at all
because they're far too picky and women
are too
promiscuous gossip social exclusion and
slander do so much harm to women and it
causes the kind of wounds that leave no
bruises or scars and the problem with
that kind of abuse is that you don't
have any physical proof of its existence
women will give terrible advice to other
women as an underhanded way of
eliminating their competition and I find
this kind of deception to be the sign of
a weak and immature mind dear men if you
see a woman who practices toxic
femininity don't date her women pass on
their morality to their children do you
want your children to inherit bad
morals all right so now I'm going to
talk about something called the
devouring
mother there are different ways in which
the devouring mother archetype comes to
fruition the term comes from Carl Young
in his analysis of the Shadow variation
of the mother and father archetypes with
the father becoming the tyrannical
father and the mother becoming the
devouring mother both terms apply to
parents who phys who psychologically
damage and impair their own children the
devouring mother emerges in different
ways but is characterized by selfishness
and
narcissism it also produces children who
are at a disadvantage in their adulthood
in each case of the devouring mother the
child is always there for her and not
not the other way
around the strength and intensity of the
maternal Instinct in women I think is
hard for men to understand or imagine I
guess it can be compared to the sex
drive that men experience as far as
intensity level men are not programmed
to raise children who aren't
biologically theirs but for women it's
incredibly easy to love someone else's
child until birth control became widely
available women used to have a lot more
children than they have today they would
typically marry young and start giving
birth to children in their early 20s the
typical American woman gave birth to
seven children on average in the 1800s
today women have one to two children on
average and they give birth later in
their
lives the social and economic climate
has mandated that women must work
full-time jobs and contribute to two
income households they're also expected
to clean the house make dinner and raise
the children men did not step into the
feminine role the same way that women
stepped into the masculine role women
are not having as many children as they
used to and this causes the maternal
instinct to become suppressed and
misdirected toward other areas of life
it comes out in subversive and unhealthy
ways one of these ways is through the
infantilization of everyone and
everything this is something that is
common among women who fulfill the
archetype of the devouring mother and is
a prominent form of toxic femininity
that often goes overlooked and
underinvestigated
infantilization takes place when someone
is being treated like a small child or a
baby when they're actually adolescence
or adults this can take the form of
coddling spoiling being condescending
making decisions for another person as
though they're
incompetent and doing things for someone
that they can do themselves this mostly
occurs in parent child relationships but
it can happen in the workplace as well
when a mother inappropriately
infantilizes her child it can NE
negatively impact that child's
self-confidence and thwart their chances
for
Independence it's fairly common to see
women who infantilize their pets baby
talking to them and pampering them as
though they were human children I'm
pretty sure this is why someone invented
sweaters for
dogs there's a movie called Interview
with a Vampire that stars Brad Pit and
Tom Cruz who plays they both play
vampires in the movie in the movie
vampires are Immortal Kirsten dun is
also in the movie and she portrays a
child vampire who never gets any older
because she was turned into aamp Empire
as a child I remember this part of the
movie bothering me quite a bit because I
was disturbed by the idea being
permanently stuck as a child forever and
never having the chance to become an
adult children who are infantilized are
kind of like that in that they remain
immature and naive into adulthood
because the adults who raised them did
everything for
them the maternal instinct is a source
of goodness in the world there's no
greater love than the love between a
mother and her child it's almost hard to
imagine how something so innocent can be
so harmful when
misdirected when someone has become
infantilized by their mother or mother
figure it decreases their capacity to
function as
adults one form of the devouring mother
is neglectful because she's engrossed in
her own world she's preoccupied with her
career and her personal and professional
goals she's more invested in her wants
and needs than the wants and needs of
her children this is the mother who has
no time for her kids because she's
always at work and pursuing her own
interests the children learn silently
that they're nothing more than an
annoyance and that their wants and needs
don't matter these are the women who
scowl at me when I tell them I'm a
stay-at-home mom they think I'm like the
scum of the earth or that I'm really
lazy but what's happening is that deep
down
my existence doesn't affirm their life
choices and they take offense to
that what women like this don't seem to
understand is that there's a tradeoff
for everything I live in a small house
it's really old I don't have a
dishwasher I've never bought a designer
handbag I get all my stuff from Goodwill
every time I go to the grocery store I
run to the discounted meat section
pushing senior citizens out of the way
and if you're one of those snobs who
would never purchase discounted meat
keep being you because that's more for
me another form of the devouring mother
is the one who is hyperfocused on
controlling the lives of her
children these mothers don't allow their
children to make mistakes or make their
own choices they're judgmental demeaning
stubborn
argumentative and they have to be right
her attitude is that Mom knows best and
that's why she keeps an eye on her
children at all times this mother is so
overbearing that her children get to the
point where they no longer have a will
of their own and they grow into insecure
adults who are too afraid of failure to
take any
risks in both cases whether she realizes
it or not the devouring mother wants her
children to remain children Mally and
fully reliant on her and this sabotage
is their future like I said earlier the
child is there for her and not the other
way around Jordan Peterson refers to
Hansel and gredle when he talks about
the devouring mother in the story the
children have a stepmother who doesn't
want them around because they interfere
with her relationship with their father
and she thinks they're not worth
feeding because of her being
inconvenienced by them they end up
getting lost in the forest and are drawn
to a house made of candy where the
narcissistic witch Lives who wants to
eat
them if you're a mother who has a
tendency to infantilize people including
your children it doesn't necessarily
make you a bad mother kids don't come
with a manual and it's easy to give in
to your maternal urges especially if you
wish you had more children than you do I
think the majority of mothers who
infantilize their children are doing so
out of Good Intentions because generally
speaking women love babies they can't
help
it we also live in a society That's Not
So Family and Child friendly as it once
was when it comes to matters of
motherhood it's very difficult to learn
how to be a mom from someone who isn't
your mom girls who grow up without
mothers and sisters have to learn about
parenting through firsthand
experience and so it's only
that many women will make mistakes along
the way as long as you're willing to
learn and you're willing to be selfless
and raising children there's always room
to grow and become a better parent think
about what your child deserves and how
you can facilitate a worthy future for
them so this is the end of the video as
always thank you for watching and
listening if you have any thoughts uh on
toxic femininity feel feel free to leave
a comment down below um have a good day
and I'll see you next time